<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Databot]]></title>
  <link href="http://data-bot.github.io/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://data-bot.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2015-01-15T00:49:15+05:30</updated>
  <id>http://data-bot.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Bharat Khatri]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Getting Started With Octopress]]></title>
    <link href="http://data-bot.github.io/blog/2015/01/15/getting-started-with-octopress/"/>
    <updated>2015-01-15T00:39:42+05:30</updated>
    <id>http://data-bot.github.io/blog/2015/01/15/getting-started-with-octopress</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Octopress is a blogging framework built over <a href="http://jekyllrb.com">Jekyll</a><sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" rel="footnote">1</a></sup>.</p>

<h4>Why Octopress?</h4>

<p>I did not choose Octopress over the <a href="https://www.staticgen.com">others</a> for specific reasons, and I <em>might</em> switch to something else in future.</p>

<p>Octopress uses <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rake_%28software%29">Rake</a><sup id="fnref:2"><a href="#fn:2" rel="footnote">2</a></sup> to expose all of its functionality. The Rake utility uses Rakefiles as input. Most of the stuff in Octopress is defined as Rake tasks, and it&rsquo;s good to understand some of these tasks in detail before you start working with Octopress.</p>

<h4>Rake tasks in Octopress<sup id="fnref:3"><a href="#fn:3" rel="footnote">3</a></sup></h4>

<ul>
<li><code>install</code></li>
</ul>


<p>This is the first Rake task to run after installing Octopress. It creates three top level directories: <code>source</code> (contatining the site source), <code>sass</code> (containing Sass files to generate site stylesheets) and <code>public</code> (containing the generated site).</p>

<ul>
<li><code>setup_github_pages</code></li>
</ul>


<p>This task is used to setup Octopress with <a href="https://pages.github.com">GitHub Pages</a>. It creates the <code>_deploy</code> directory which is used for deploying the generated site to the GitHub Pages repository.</p>

<ul>
<li><code>generate</code></li>
</ul>


<p>This task calls <a href="http://compass-style.org">Compass</a> to compile the Sass files and Jekyll to build the site. The generated site is stored in the <code>public</code> directory and contains everything your site needs in order to be served off a static file server.</p>

<ul>
<li><code>preview</code></li>
</ul>


<p>This task helps you preview the site on your local machine. It also monitors the <code>source</code> and <code>sass</code> directories for changes and regenerates the site if needed.</p>

<ul>
<li><code>deploy</code></li>
</ul>


<p>This task is used to deploy the site. The generated site is copied from the <code>public</code> directory to the <code>_deploy</code> directory and pushed to the GitHub Pages repository.</p>
<div class="footnotes">
<hr/>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1">
<p>Jekyll is an open source blog-aware static site generator written in Ruby.<a href="#fnref:1" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
<li id="fn:2">
<p>Rake is a Make-like program implemented in Ruby, and Rakefiles (equivalent of Makefiles in Make) use Ruby syntax.<a href="#fnref:2" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
<li id="fn:3">
<p>All Rake tasks in the <a href="https://github.com/imathis/octopress/blob/master/Rakefile">Rakefile</a> have not been discussed here.<a href="#fnref:3" rev="footnote">&#8617;</a></p></li>
</ol>
</div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
